<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3"?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc comments="yes"?>
<?rfc inline="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<rfc category="std" docName="draft-reddy-dots-telemetry-00" ipr="trust200902">
  <front>
    <title
    abbrev="DOTS Telemetry for Efficient Protective Networking">Distributed
    Denial-of-Service Open Threat Signaling (DOTS) Telemetry</title>

    <author fullname="Tirumaleswar Reddy" initials="T." surname="Reddy">
      <organization abbrev="McAfee">McAfee, Inc.</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Embassy Golf Link Business Park</street>

          <city>Bangalore</city>

          <region>Karnataka</region>

          <code>560071</code>

          <country>India</country>
        </postal>

        <email>kondtir@gmail.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Mohamed Boucadair" initials="M." surname="Boucadair">
      <organization>Orange</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street></street>

          <city>Rennes</city>

          <code>35000</code>

          <country>France</country>
        </postal>

        <email>mohamed.boucadair@orange.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Ehud Doron" initials="E." surname="Doron">
      <organization>Radware Ltd.</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Raoul Wallenberg Street</street>

          <city>Tel-Aviv</city>

          <code>69710</code>

          <country>Israel</country>
        </postal>

        <email>ehudd@radware.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date day="1" month="July" year="2019" />

    <workgroup>DOTS</workgroup>

    <abstract>
      <t>This document aims to enrich DOTS signal channel protocol with
      various telemetry attributes allowing optimal DDoS attack mitigation.
      This document specifies the normal traffic baseline and attack traffic
      telemetry attributes a DOTS client can convey to its DOTS server in the
      mitigation request, the mitigation status telemetry attributes a DOTS
      server can communicate to a DOTS client, and the mitigation efficacy
      telemetry attributes a DOTS client can communicate to a DOTS server. The
      telemetry attributes can assist the mitigator to choose the DDoS
      mitigation techniques and perform optimal DDoS attack mitigation.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section anchor="introduction" title="Introduction">
      <t>The Internet security 'battle' between the adversary and security
      countermeasures is an everlasting one. DDoS attacks have become more
      vicious and sophisticated in almost all aspects of their maneuvers and
      malevolent intentions. IT organizations and service providers are facing
      DDoS attacks that fall into two broad categories: Network/Transport
      layer attacks and Application layer attacks. Network/Transport layer
      attacks target the victim's infrastructure. These attacks are not
      necessarily aimed at taking down the actual delivered services, but
      rather to eliminate various network elements (routers, switches,
      firewalls, transit links, and so on) from serving legitimate user
      traffic. The main method of such attacks is to send a large volume or
      high PPS of traffic toward the victim's infrastructure. Typically,
      attack volumes may vary from a few 100 Mbps/PPS to 100s of Gbps or even
      Tbps. Attacks are commonly carried out leveraging botnets and attack
      reflectors for amplification attacks, such as NTP, DNS, SNMP, SSDP, and
      so on. Application layer attacks target various applications. Typical
      examples include attacks against HTTP/HTTPS, DNS, SIP, SMTP, and so on.
      However, all valid applications with their port numbers open at network
      edges can be attractive attack targets. Application layer attacks are
      considered more complex and hard to categorize, therefore harder to
      detect and mitigate efficiently.</t>

      <t>To compound the problem, attackers also leverage multi-vectored
      attacks. These merciless attacks are assembled from dynamic attack
      vectors (Network/Application) and tactics. As such, multiple attack
      vectors formed by multiple attack types and volumes are launched
      simultaneously towards a victim. Multi-vector attacks are harder to
      detect and defend. Multiple and simultaneous mitigation techniques are
      needed to defeat such attack campaigns. It is also common for attackers
      to change attack vectors right after a successful mitigation, burdening
      their opponents with changing their defense methods.</t>

      <t>The ultimate conclusion derived from these real scenarios is that
      modern attacks detection and mitigation are most certainly complicated
      and highly convoluted tasks. They demand a comprehensive knowledge of
      the attack attributes, the targeted normal behavior/ traffic patterns,
      as well as the attacker's on-going and past actions. Even more
      challenging, retrieving all the analytics needed for detecting these
      attacks is not simple to obtain with the industry's current
      capabilities.</t>

      <t>The DOTS signal channel protocol <xref
      target="I-D.ietf-dots-signal-channel"></xref> is used to carry
      information about a network resource or a network (or a part thereof)
      that is under a Distributed Denial of Service (DDoS) attack. Such
      information is sent by a DOTS client to one or multiple DOTS servers so
      that appropriate mitigation actions are undertaken on traffic deemed
      suspicious. Various use cases are discussed in <xref
      target="I-D.ietf-dots-use-cases"></xref>.</t>

      <t>Typically, DOTS clients can be integrated within a DDoS attack
      detector, or network and security elements that have been actively
      engaged with ongoing attacks. The DOTS client mitigation environment
      determines that it is no longer possible or practical for it to handle
      these attacks. This can be due to lack of resources or security
      capabilities, as derived from the complexities and the intensity of
      these attacks. In this circumstance, the DOTS client has invaluable
      knowledge about the actual attacks that need to be handled by the DOTS
      server. By enabling the DOTS client to share this comprehensive
      knowledge of an ongoing attack under specific circumstances, the DOTS
      server can drastically increase its abilities to accomplish successful
      mitigation. While the attack is being handled by the DOTS server
      associated mitigation resources, the DOTS server has the knowledge about
      the ongoing attack mitigation. The DOTS server can share this
      information with the DOTS client so that the client can better assess
      and evaluate the actual mitigation realized.</t>

      <t>In some deployments, DOTS clients can send mitigation hints derived
      from attack details to DOTS servers, with the full understanding that
      the DOTS server may ignore mitigation hints, as described in <xref
      target="RFC8612"></xref> (Gen-004). Mitigation hints will be transmitted
      across the DOTS signal channel, as the data channel may not be
      functional during an attack. How a DOTS server is handling normal and
      attack traffic attributes, and mitigation hints is
      implementation-specific.</t>

      <t>Both DOTS client and server can benefit this information by
      presenting various information in relevant management, reporting, and
      portal systems.</t>

      <t>This document defines DOTS telemetry attributes the DOTS client can
      convey to the DOTS server, and vice versa. The DOTS telemetry attributes
      are not mandatory fields. Nevertheless, when DOTS telemetry attributes
      are available to a DOTS agent, and absent any policy, it can signal the
      attributes in order to optimize the overall mitigation service
      provisioned using DOTS. Some of the DOTS telemetry data are not shared
      during an attack time.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="notation" title="Terminology">
      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
      "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "NOT RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and
      "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as described in BCP 14
      <xref target="RFC2119"></xref><xref target="RFC8174"></xref> when, and
      only when, they appear in all capitals, as shown here.</t>

      <t>The reader should be familiar with the terms defined in <xref
      target="RFC8612"></xref>.</t>

      <t>"DOTS Telemetry" is defined as the collection of attributes that are
      used to characterize normal traffic baseline, attacks and their
      mitigation measures, and any related information that may help in
      enforcing countermeasures. The DOTS Telemetry is an optional set of
      attributes that can be signaled in the DOTS signal channel protocol.</t>

      <t>The meaning of the symbols in YANG tree diagrams is defined in <xref
      target="RFC8340"></xref>.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="overview" title="DOTS Telemetry: Overview &amp; Purpose">
      <t>When signaling a mitigation request, it is most certainly beneficial
      for the DOTS client to signal to the DOTS server any knowledge regarding
      ongoing attacks. This can happen in cases where DOTS clients are asking
      the DOTS server for support in defending against attacks that they have
      already detected and/or mitigated. These actions taken by DOTS clients
      are referred to as "signaling the DOTS Telemetry".</t>

      <t>If attacks are already detected and categorized by the DOTS client
      domain, the DOTS server, and its associated mitigation services, can
      proactively benefit this information and optimize the overall service
      delivered. It is important to note that DOTS client and server detection
      and mitigation approaches can be different, and can potentially outcome
      different results and attack classifications. The DDoS mitigation
      service treats the ongoing attack details from the client as hints and
      cannot completely rely or trust the attack details conveyed by the DOTS
      client. </t>

      <t>A basic requirement of security operation teams is to be aware and
      get visibility into the attacks they need to handle. The DOTS server
      security operation teams benefit from the DOTS telemetry, especially
      from the reports of ongoing attacks. Even if some mitigation can be
      automated, operational teams can use the DOTS telemetry to be prepared
      for attack mitigation and to assign the correct resources (operation
      staff, networking and mitigation) for the specific service. Similarly,
      security operation personnel at the DOTS client side ask for feedback
      about their requests for protection. Therefore, it is valuable for the
      DOTS server to share DOTS telemetry with the DOTS client. Thus mutual
      sharing of information is crucial for "closing the mitigation loop"
      between the DOTS client and server. For the server side team, it is
      important to realize that the same attacks that the DOTS server's
      mitigation resources are seeing are those that the DOTS client is asking
      to mitigate. For the DOTS client side team, it is important to realize
      that the DOTS clients receive the required service. For example:
      understanding that "I asked for mitigation of two attacks and my DOTS
      server detects and mitigates only one...". Cases of inconsistency in
      attack classification between DOTS client and server can be
      high-lighted, and maybe handled, using the DOTS telemetry
      attributes.</t>

      <t>In addition, management and orchestration systems, at both DOTS
      client and server sides, can potentially use DOTS telemetry as a
      feedback to automate various control and management activities derived
      from ongoing information signaled.</t>

      <t>If the DOTS server's mitigation resources have the capabilities to
      facilitate the DOTS telemetry, the DOTS server adopts its protection
      strategy and activates the required countermeasures immediately
      (automation enabled). The overall results of this adoption are optimized
      attack mitigation decisions and actions.</t>

      <t>The DOTS telemetry can also be used to tune the DDoS mitigators with
      the correct state of the attack. During the last few years, DDoS attack
      detection technologies have evolved from threshold-based detection (that
      is, cases when all or specific parts of traffic cross a pre-defined
      threshold for a certain period of time is considered as an attack) to an
      "anomaly detection" approach. In anomaly detection, the main idea is to
      maintain rigorous learning of "normal" behavior and where an "anomaly"
      (or an attack) is identified and categorized based on the knowledge
      about the normal behavior and a deviation from this normal behavior.
      Machine learning approaches are used such that the actual "traffic
      thresholds" are "automatically calculated" by learning the protected
      entity normal traffic behavior during peace time. The normal traffic
      characterization learned is referred to as the "normal traffic
      baseline". An attack is detected when the victim's actual traffic is
      deviating from this normal baseline.</t>

      <t>In addition, subsequent activities toward mitigating an attack are
      much more challenging. The ability to distinguish legitimate traffic
      from attacker traffic on a per packet basis is complex. This complexity
      originates from the fact that the packet itself may look "legitimate"
      and no attack signature can be identified. The anomaly can be identified
      only after detailed statistical analysis. DDoS attack mitigators use the
      normal baseline during the mitigation of an attack to identify and
      categorize the expected appearance of a specific traffic pattern.
      Particularly the mitigators use the normal baseline to recognize the
      "level of normality" needs to be achieved during the various mitigation
      process.</t>

      <t>Normal baseline calculation is performed based on continuous learning
      of the normal behavior of the protected entities. The minimum learning
      period varies from hours to days and even weeks, depending on the
      protected application behavior. The baseline cannot be learned during
      active attacks because attack conditions do not characterize the
      protected entities' normal behavior.</t>

      <t>If the DOTS client has calculated the normal baseline of its
      protected entities, signaling this attribute to the DOTS server along
      with the attack traffic levels is significantly valuable. The DOTS
      server benefits from this telemetry by tuning its mitigation resources
      with the DOTS client's normal baseline. The DOTS server mitigators use
      the baseline to familiarize themselves with the attack victim's normal
      behavior and target the baseline as the level of normality they need to
      achieve. Consequently, the overall mitigation performances obtained are
      dramatically improved in terms of time to mitigate, accuracy,
      false-negative, false-positive, and other measures.</t>

      <t>Mitigation of attacks without having certain knowledge of normal
      traffic can be inaccurate at best. This is especially true for recursive
      signaling (see Section 3.2.3 in <xref
      target="I-D.ietf-dots-use-cases"></xref>). In addition, the highly
      diverse types of use-cases where DOTS clients are integrated also
      emphasize the need for knowledge of client behavior. Consequently,
      common global thresholds for attack detection practically cannot be
      realized. Each DOTS client can have its own levels of traffic and normal
      behavior. Without facilitating normal baseline signaling, it may be very
      difficult for DOTS servers in some cases to detect and mitigate the
      attacks accurately. It is important to emphasize that it is practically
      impossible for the server's mitigators to calculate the normal baseline,
      in cases they do not have any knowledge of the traffic beforehand. In
      addition, baseline learning requires a period of time that cannot be
      afforded during active attack. Of course, this information can provided
      using out-of-band mechanisms or manual configuration at the risk to
      maintain inaccurate information as the network evolves and "normal"
      patterns change. The use of a dynamic and collaborative means between
      the DOTS client and server to identify and share key parameters for the
      sake of efficient DDoS protect is valuable.</t>

      <t>During a high volume attack, DOTS client pipes can be totally
      saturated. The DOTS client asks the DOTS server to handle the attack
      upstream so that DOTS client pipes return to a reasonable load level
      (normal pattern, ideally). At this point, it is essential to ensure that
      the DOTS server does not overwhelm the DOTS client pipes by sending back
      "clean traffic", or what it believes is "clean". This can happen when
      the server has not managed to detect and mitigate all the attacks
      launched towards the client. In this case, it can be valuable to clients
      to signal to server the "Total pipe capacity", which is the level of
      traffic the clients can absorb from the upstream server. Dynamic
      updating of the condition of pipes between DOTS agents while they are
      under a DDoS attack is essential. For example, for cases of multiple
      DOTS clients share the same physical connectivity pipes. It is important
      to note, that the term "pipe" noted here does not necessary represent
      physical pipe, but rather represents the current level of traffic client
      can observe from server. The server should activate other mechanisms to
      ensure it does not saturate the client's pipes unintentionally. The
      rate-limit action defined in <xref
      target="I-D.ietf-dots-data-channel"></xref> can be a reasonable
      candidate to achieve this objective; the client can ask for the type of
      traffic (such as ICMP, UDP, TCP port 80) it prefers to limit.</t>

      <t>To summarize, timely and effective signaling of up-to-date DOTS
      telemetry to all elements involved in the mitigation process is
      essential and absolutely improves the overall service effectiveness.
      Bi-directional feedback between DOTS agents is required for the
      increased awareness of each party, supporting superior and highly
      efficient attack mitigation service.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="DOTS Telemetry Attributes ">
      <t>This section outlines the set of DOTS telemetry attributes. The
      ultimate objective of these attributes is to allow for the complete
      knowledge of attacks and the various particulars that can best
      characterize attacks.</t>

      <t>The description and motivation behind each attribute were presented
      in <xref target="overview"></xref>. DOTS telemetry attributes are
      optionally signaled and therefore MUST NOT be treated as mandatory
      fields in the DOTS signal channel protocol.</t>

      <section title="Pre-mitigation DOTS Telemetry Attributes">
        <t>The following pre-mitigation telemetry attributes can be signaled
        from the DOTS client to the DOTS server.<list style="symbols">
            <t>DISCUSSION NOTES: (1) Some telemetry can be communicated using
            DOTS data channel. (2) Evaluate the risk of fragmentation, or (3)
            check if we can define a dedicated URI for telemetry (e.g.: use
            ./telemetry). Some of the information is not specific to each
            mitigation request.</t>
          </list></t>

        <section title="Total Traffic Normal Baseline">
          <t>The low percentile (10th percentile), mid percentile (50th
          percentile), high percentile (90th percentile) and peak values of
          "Total traffic normal baselines" measured in kilobytes per second or
          megabytes per second or gigabytes per second.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Total Pipe Capability">
          <t>The limit of traffic volume, in kilobytes per second or megabytes
          per second or gigabytes per second. This attribute represents the
          DOTS client domain pipe limit.<list style="symbols">
              <t>NOTE: Multi-homing case to be considered.</t>
            </list></t>
        </section>

        <section title="Total Attack Traffic ">
          <t>The low percentile (10th percentile), mid percentile (50th
          percentile), high percentile (90th percentile) and peak values of
          total attack traffic measured in kilobytes per second or megabytes
          per second or gigabytes per second.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Total Traffic ">
          <t>The low percentile (10th percentile), mid percentile (50th
          percentile), high percentile (90th percentile) and peak values of
          total traffic during a DDoS attack measured in kilobytes per second
          or megabytes per second gigabytes per second.</t>
        </section>

        <section anchor="attackdetails" title="Attack Details">
          <t>Various information and details that describe the on-going
          attacks that needs to be mitigated by the DOTS server. The attack
          details need to cover well-known and common attacks (such as a SYN
          Flood) along with new emerging or vendor-specific attacks. The
          following fields describing the on-going attack are discussed:</t>

          <t><list style="hanging">
              <t hangText="vendor-id:">Vendor ID is a security vendor's
              Enterprise Number as registered with IANA <xref
              target="Enterprise-Numbers"></xref>. It is a four-byte integer
              value. <vspace blankLines="1" />This is a mandatory
              sub-attribute.</t>

              <t hangText="attack-id:">Unique identifier assigned by the
              vendor for the attack. <vspace blankLines="1" />This is a
              mandatory sub-attribute.</t>

              <t hangText="attack-name:">Textual representation of attack
              description. Natural Language Processing (e.g., word embedding)
              can possibly be used to map the attack description to an attack
              type. Textual representation of attack solves two problems (a)
              avoids the need to create mapping tables manually between
              vendors (2) Avoids the need to standardize attack types which
              keep evolving. <vspace blankLines="1" />This is a mandatory
              sub-attribute</t>

              <t hangText="attack-severity:">Attack severity. Emergency (0),
              critical (1) and alert (2). <vspace blankLines="1" />This is an
              optional sub-attribute</t>
            </list></t>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section title="DOTS Client to Server Mitigation Efficacy DOTS Telemetry Attributes">
        <t>The mitigation efficacy telemetry attributes can be signaled from
        the DOTS client to the DOTS server as part of the periodic mitigation
        efficacy updates to the server.</t>

        <section title="Total Attack Traffic ">
          <t>The low percentile (10th percentile), mid percentile (50th
          percentile), high percentile (90th percentile) and peak values of
          total attack traffic the DOTS client still sees during the active
          mitigation service measured in kilobytes per second or megabytes per
          second or gigabytes per second.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Attack Details">
          <t>The overall attack details as observed from the DOTS client
          perspective during the active mitigation service. The same
          attributes defined in <xref target="attackdetails"></xref> are
          applicable here.</t>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section title="DOTS Server to Client Mitigation Status DOTS Telemetry Attributes ">
        <t>The mitigation status telemetry attributes can be signaled from the
        DOTS server to the DOTS client as part of the periodic mitigation
        status update.</t>

        <section title="Mitigation Status">
          <t>As defined in <xref target="RFC8612"></xref>, the actual
          mitigation activities can include several countermeasure mechanisms.
          The DOTS server SHOULD signal the current operational status to each
          relevant countermeasure. A list of attacks detected by each
          countermeasure. The same attributes defined for <xref
          target="attackdetails"></xref> are applicable here for describing
          the attacks detected and mitigated.</t>
        </section>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="YANG" title="DOTS Telemetry YANG Module">
      <section anchor="tree" title="Tree Structure">
        <t>TODO</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="module" title="YANG Module">
        <t>TODO</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
      <section anchor="map" title="DOTS Signal Channel CBOR Mappings Registry">
        <t>This specification registers the DOTS telemetry attributes in the
        IANA "DOTS Signal Channel CBOR Mappings" registry established by <xref
        target="I-D.ietf-dots-signal-channel"></xref>.</t>

        <t>The DOTS telemetry attributes defined in this specification are
        comprehension-optional parameters.</t>

        <t><list style="symbols">
            <t>Note to the RFC Editor: Please delete (TBD1)-(TBD5) once CBOR
            keys are assigned from the 0x8000 - 0xBFFF range.</t>
          </list><figure align="center">
            <artwork><![CDATA[+-------------------+------------+--------+---------------+--------+
| Parameter Name    | YANG       | CBOR   | CBOR Major    | JSON   |
|                   | Type       | Key    |    Type &     | Type   |
|                   |            |        | Information   |        |
+-------------------+------------+--------+---------------+--------+
| TODO              |            |        |               |        |
+-------------------+------------+--------+---------------+--------+
]]></artwork>
          </figure></t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="yang" title="DOTS Signal Telemetry YANG Module">
        <t>This document requests IANA to register the following URI in the
        "ns" subregistry within the "IETF XML Registry" <xref
        target="RFC3688"></xref>: <figure>
            <artwork><![CDATA[         URI: urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:yang:TODO
         Registrant Contact: The IESG.
         XML: N/A; the requested URI is an XML namespace.]]></artwork>
          </figure>This document requests IANA to register the following YANG
        module in the "YANG Module Names" subregistry <xref
        target="RFC7950"></xref> within the "YANG Parameters" registry.<figure>
            <artwork><![CDATA[         name: ietf-dots-telemetry
         namespace: urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:yang:TODO
         maintained by IANA: N
         prefix: dots-telemetry
         reference: RFC XXXX
]]></artwork>
          </figure></t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>Security considerations in <xref
      target="I-D.ietf-dots-signal-channel"></xref> need to be taken into
      consideration.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="ack" title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>The authors would like to thank Flemming Andreasen, Liang Xia, and
      Kaname Nishizuka co-authors of
      https://tools.ietf.org/html/draft-doron-dots-telemetry-00 draft and
      everyone who had contributed to that document.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.7950"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.3688"?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.8174'?>

      <?rfc include="reference.I-D.ietf-dots-signal-channel" ?>

      <?rfc include="reference.I-D.ietf-dots-data-channel" ?>

      <reference anchor="Enterprise-Numbers"
                 target="http://www.iana.org/         assignments/enterprise-numbers.html">
        <front>
          <title>Private Enterprise Numbers</title>

          <author>
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <date year="2005" />
        </front>
      </reference>
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.8612"?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.ietf-dots-use-cases'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.8340'?>
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
